Guide to the Coalition of Private University Students (COPUS) Records, 1970 - 1981
Coalition of Private University Students (COPUS) Records, 1970 - 1981
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Coalition of Private University Students (COPUS)
1000-162
0.25
1
COPUS, the Coalition of Private University Students, was a financial aid advocacy group that was formed in the mid 1970s when a coalition of college students across the country joined together to address financial aid issues.
This collection contains documents that are related to or from the group COPUS either nationally or on the Wesleyan campus. It includes statistics and information on Wesleyan's financial aid policies and other policies, and information on COPUS's involvement in Washington, D.C. and lobbying for change in the 1980s budget cuts. There are also documents such as notes and flyers from seminars held by COPUS on campus as well as Wesleyan and Middletown, Connecticut-area press on the group's activities.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Acquired between 1984 and 1997
Historical Note
COPUS, the Coalition of Private University Students, was a financial aid advocacy group that was formed in the mid 1970s when a coalition of college students across the country joined together to address financial aid issues. The group's immediate goals in the 1970s were to uphold the gains that middle- and low-income students made during the 1960s. Exclusionary economics in the 1970s made it more difficult for these students to afford high priced state schools and independent schools. Thus COPUS became active throughout campuses to make sure the goals of the 1960s were upheld through the 1970's. Their activism became more involved in government policy towards the late 1970s through the mid 1980s.
In 1983, while President Ronald Reagan was in office, billions in federal funds were cut for financial aid for students attending private universities. In response, COPUS began to apply political pressure to oppose the budget cut. This cut threatened enrollment in private universities and students felt that they had a right to federal aid to private universities if qualified. Students sought to halt the budget cut so as to reinstate eligibility of lower income students to attend private universities.
COPUS members at Wesleyan University were particularly passionate about the subject of aid-blind admissions and federal financial aid because of the social-activist history at Wesleyan. The curriculum, resources, and ideology of Wesleyan, as well as the diversity of its student population, had all been reshaped in the 1960s. COPUS members believed that if federal financial aid were to cease to exist, it would compromise the ideal of Wesleyan University as a diverse place for higher learning. This threat, along with the fact that many students studying at the time were being directly affected by this policy, caused Wesleyan students to become very concerned with the federal financial aid budget cuts.
In 1982 and 1983, hundreds of Wesleyan students participated in rallies in Washington, D.C. on National Student Lobbying Day. These rallies were considered successful, yet the budget cut was still under consideration. Wesleyan COPUS members gained support from both Wesleyan faculty and Democratic senators and representatives. Supporters of COPUS called for their elected representatives to lobby for the cause on behalf of students. The group was so involved in lobbyist activities, they even wrote to President Reagan himself At a rally in front of Davenport Campus Center, COPUS members displayed photos in the year book in which they had stamped withdrawn for financial reasons over the faces of students who were not able to graduate due to financial aid cuts. A copy of this yearbook was sent directly to President Reagan to emphasize that the future of higher education was at stake.
Collection Overview
This collection contains documents that are related to or from the group COPUS either nationally or on the Wesleyan campus. The first folder contains information on the group, including statistics and information on Wesleyan's financial aid policies. The second folder contains more in-depth documents on COPUS involvement on the Wesleyan campus. COPUS collected information on professor course loads, teacher evaluations, memos to the board of trustees, and correspondence between Wesleyan faculty and the President of the University. The third folder contains mainly information on COPUS's involvement in Washington, D.C. and lobbying for change in the 1980s budget cuts. The folder includes letters written to various state representatives as well as various press on the group and nation-wide newsletters. The collection includes documents such as notes and flyers from seminars held by COPUS on campus as well as Wesleyan and Middletown-area press on the group's activities.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Coalition of Private University Students (COPUS); Student aid--Connecticut.; Student aid--Education (Higher)--United States.; Student financial aid administration--Connecticut.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Administration.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Finance.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History--20th century.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Universities and colleges--Admission.; College costs --United States.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Background Information
    Documents pertain to Aid-Blind Admissions Policy and include statistics, correspondence and official reports. Faculty compensation studies, tenure and teacher load studies are also included. All material from 1970s to early 1980s.
    - Wesleyan Aid-Blind Admissions Policy Statistics (Folder 1)
    - Wesleyan Aid-Blind Admissions Policy StatisticLetter from President Campbell, 1970 (Folder 1)
    - Report of the Student Budget Committee of the Wesleyan Student Assembly on the increasing of the College Body Fund, 1978 (Folder 1)
    - College Body Constitution, 1978 (Folder 1)
    - Address by President Campbell, 1979 (Folder 1)
    - Aid Blind Admissions Policy, 1981 (Folder 1)
    - A Small College of Liberal Arts and Sciences (Folder 1)
    - Winter, David - Psychology (Folder 1)
  - Wesleyan Financial Aid Involvement
    - Report of Educational Policy Committee on General Education at Wesleyan University (Folder 2)
    - Allocation of Faculty Resources: Responses of Department Chains (Folder 2)
    - Memo to N. Greene: Course/Class overcrowding (Folder 2)
    - Educational Rationale (Folder 2)
    - Supplemental Educational Opportunity Grant (SEOG) (Folder 2)
    - Teaching Loads, 1976 (Folder 2)
    - Faculty Compensation Study, 1978 (Folder 2)
    - Report of the Wesleyan Student Assembly Ad Hoc Committee on Tenure, 1980 (Folder 2)
    - Letter to Faculty from the President, 1980 (Folder 2)
    - Memo to Board of Trustees: Recommendations Regarding a Five-Year Financial Framework, 1980 (Folder 2)
    - Letter to N. Greene from Faculty Planning Committee, 1981 (Folder 2)
    - Submission of Teacher Evaluations, 1981 (Folder 2)
  - Legislative Involvement
    - Letter to Larry Starfield: COPUS organizing in Connecticut, 1975 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - COPUS and Connecticut Legislature, 1975 (Folder 3)
    - Letter to Trinity, 1975 (Folder 3)
    - Letter to Consortium on Financing Higher Education, 1975 (Folder 3)
    - Memo: COPUS Organizing in Connecticut, 1975 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS statement, 1976 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Newsletter, 1976 (Folder 3)
    - Memoranda, 1976 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with Commission for Higher Education and legislature, 1976 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - Connecticut Universities and COPUS, 1976 (Folder 3)
    - Invitation to COPUS meeting, 1976 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS committee membership, 1976-1977 (Folder 3)
    - Legislative Issues Conference, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - Press Release: COPUS Expands Campus Activities, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Memorandum to Connecticut Chapters, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Connecticut Chapters, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - Letter to Financial Aid Director, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - Connecticut Conference of Independent Colleges: Memo, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS to do list and room request, 1977 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS membership and fundraising sign up, 1977-1978 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Memo: from Larry Starfield, 1977-1978 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS meeting flyer, 1977-1978 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Newsletter 1977-1978 (Folder 3)
    - Wesleyan University Facility Request- Tuition Seminar, 1978 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS proposal, 1978 (Folder 3)
    - Agenda for COPUS Briefing, 1978 (Folder 3)
    - Letters to Mr. Campbell: Tuition Seminar, 1978-1979 (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Summer update, 1978 (Folder 3)
    - Higher Education Daily, 1978 (Folder 3)
    - Student Employment Possibilities, 1978-1979 (Folder 3)
    - Outline for Parent's Night/College Night Presentation (Folder 3)
    - Financial Aid Seminar notes (Folder 3)
    - Financial Aid Seminar Flyer (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Committee Membership (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence- House of Representatives and COPUS (Folder 3)
    - COPUS in brief (Folder 3)
    - COPUS statement/letter: hand written (Folder 3)
    - Reasons for a College Access Program (Folder 3)
    - Connecticut Legislative Issues Affecting Independent College Students (Folder 3)
    - Major Federal Issues Affecting Independent College Students (Folder 3)
    - Phone List: handwritten (Folder 3)
    - COPUS Memo: Phone calls (Folder 3)
    - COPUS statement (Folder 3)
    - Memorandum to All COPUS chapters (Folder 3)
    - COPUS membership names and numbers- handwritten (Folder 3)
    - Constitution of the Connecticut Independent Student Coalition CISC (Folder 3)
    - COPUS - Wesleyan Activities (Folder 3)
    - Staffing the COPUS office (Folder 3)
    - Letter to COPUS from Linda Sears- Re: Office Responsibilities (Folder 3)
    - Institutional Membership (Folder 3)
  - News Articles
    - Wesleyan Argus: Students Lobbying On Aid, 1975 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: COPUS Testifies Before Gov. Grasso, 1976 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: Higher Education News, 1976 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: Grasso's Proposed Budget Brings Increase in Aid, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: COPUS Continues Cost Crisis Clamor, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: COPUS Asks Dodd's Support for Increases in Financial Aid, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: COPUS Asks Dodd's Support Increases in Financial Aid, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: COPUS to Start Aid Counseling, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Hermes: COPUS Works for Change, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: September 9, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: September 27, 1977 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: Ct. Group Join Forces; Corhaus to Head Nat. Bd. 1978 (Folder 4)
    - Wesleyan Argus: Financial Aid Gets Help (Folder 4)
    - The Middletown Press: WES Group Works to Boost Independent Student Aid (Folder 4)